All right, בוקר טוב, boker tov, so today's דף daf is נ"ז
עמוד ב'. nun zayin bet. We pick up in the middle of
נ"ז עמוד ב' nun zayin bet and we pick up from תשמע
tashma 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 lines down, pretty much beginning of
the line. And the point here is now looking at the statement
of שמואל. Shmuel. Until שמואל Shmuel we understood that there were two
things: actually seeing blood and a כתם, kesem, a stain. Stains, A,
might not have been טמא tamei at all if you could attribute
it to something else, and B, even when they were טמא tamei
they were only דרבנן. derabbanan. The assumption had been in all of
the משניות mishnayot and everything without prior to שמואל Shmuel that that
was because there was always an element of doubt whether the stain
was from the woman or not. We'll see another reason later today.
But שמואל Shmuel says that there's a new criteria called הרגשה hargasha
and that without a woman having a sensation in her body, then
she's never going to be a נדה דאורייתא niddah de'oraisa and all
stains are at most rabbinic, which the גמרא Gemara will say because
it was not accompanied with a sensation. And that's critically important today
for determining if something is a כתם kesem or not. And the
גמרא Gemara is now analyzing that, we will discuss, I'll go back
to discuss the implications in a minute, but let's take a look
now at the גמרא Gemara which tries to prove or disprove this
statement of שמואל. Shmuel. תשמע, tashma, come in here. נמצאת היא אומרת
ג' ספקות בטהרה: nimtzas hi omeres gimel sefeikos betahara: there are three
doubts with regards to a woman with questions about whether a stain
is hers or not. I mean at least this is categorizing it
as three. What are the three? על בשרה, al besarah, if she
finds a stain on her body, on her flesh, then, I mean
a stain, blood, then ספק טמא ספק טהור טמא. safek tamei safek
tahor tamei. It's doubt whether it's from her or not, from her,
whether it's טמא tamei or טהור, tahor, טמא. tamei. You're going to
assume without evidence to the contrary that it's coming from her and
that she is טמאה temeiah since she's נדה. niddah. על חלוקה, al
chalukah, if it's on her garment, ספק טמא ספק טהור טהור. safek
tamei safek tahor tahor. Then there's some element of doubt, then טהור.
tahor. Then unless there's, you know, sort of strong evidence to indicate
that it's from her, you'll assume it's from elsewhere. Obviously this is
again in a time where they have a lot of blood flying
around all over the place. Okay, so this basically indicates that the
issue about stains is where it came from. You're more assume when
it's on her that it came from her, when it's on her
garment you're more assume it came from elsewhere. That's the basic ספק.
safek.
I mean if it's, you know, in a place where you'd think
it's hers.
Right, right. ובמגעות ובהסיטות הלך אחר הרוב. u've'maga'os u've'hesseisos halach achar harov.
And when it comes to touching and moving, you go after the
majority. Now what does that exactly mean? So רש"י Rashi says what
that means is that a woman, not that she has a stain,
but that she's just very often she gets her period, she doesn't
know when she gets her period, I mean she has no regularity
when she gets her period. So in that type of a case,
is she טמאה, temeiah, is she not טמאה, temeiah, you go by
the majority whether the majority of the time she's seeing or not
seeing. תוספות Tosafos sort of strongly disagrees with this. תוספות Tosafos says
what do you mean, we always say if a woman doesn't have
her period, we never say that we assume that she's טמאה temeiah
half the time. So
or whatever. So תוספות Tosafos says that what we're really talking about
is, let me just double check תוספות Tosafos again,
תוספות מגעות. Tosafos maga'os.
Yeah,
so תוספות Tosafos basically just says that we're still going back to
the stain being found on the garment. And even though the stain
is found on the garment and we have just gotten through saying
that when the stain is found on the garment we'll normally be
likely to attribute it to elsewhere, but that's unless it's the type
of a woman that is very often bleeding. If it's a woman
that is very often getting her period on a very frequent basis,
then even when it's found on her garment we'll be inclined to
attribute it to her. So that's how תוספות Tosafos reads it. מגעות
והסיטות maga'os ve'hesseisos means she's touching and moving. Right. Why he shifted
that phrase I don't know. Anyway, that's basically the point: if there's
a doubt and it's on her you say it's from her, if
it's on her garment you're more inclined to say it's from elsewhere.
And way תוספות Tosafos reads the rest phrase is unless there's more
of a reason to think that it's from her, that very often
she's bleeding, and then you would attribute it back to her. Anyway,
מאי הלך אחר הרוב? mai halach achar harov? The point of the
גמרא Gemara is that there's an element of a doubt and when
there's an element of a doubt we use certain indicators like majority
and whatever to determine where it came from. So לאו דאמרת אם
רוב ימיה טמאים טמאה? lav de'amras im rov yameha teme'im temeiah? If
most of the days she, you know, she most often, I mean
obviously it has to be a real condition, but that she's bleeding
most of the time, then you'll assume it came from her. ואף
על גב דלא ארגשה. ve'af al gav de'la argashah. But again the
גמרא's Gemara's point is if there's a doubt, the only way there's
a doubt is if she's not having a sensation. If she's having
a sensation, then that's a clear indicator that she's bleeding. So if
it says if there's a doubt and most of the time, you
know, she might be bleeding you attribute it to her, presumably that
means even without a sensation and you see that you make her
טמאה temeiah even without a sensation. So the גמרא Gemara says לא,
lo, no, that's not what it means. It means אם רוב ימיה
בהרגשה חזיא טמאה. im rov yameha be'hargashah chazya temeiah. If most of
the time she bleeds with a sensation and then you find that
she's bleeding very frequently and then you find a stain, then you
assume it's from her. Ah, there's no sensation this time. So now
the גמרא Gemara introduces a new idea. דאימור ארגשה ולאו אדעתה. de'eima
argashah ve'lav ada'atah. Maybe she had a sensation without realizing it. Now
most people first of all hear that and think that's absurd. How
can she... After all, sensation means that you realize it. How can
you have it without? But I actually, when I talk to my
students about this, I say it's really not so absurd. There are
very often things that we might have, be have a sensation of,
but not pay attention to. Like I say, feel the weight of
your watch on your hand, on your, you know, on your arm,
or your glasses on your nose if you're wearing glasses. Right? If
you stop and pay attention, you could actually feel their weight, but
until I told you to do that, you were completely oblivious to
it. So there could be some types of things that are sensations
in our bodies which we're not focused on, and you know, and
maybe that they're happening but we're not paying attention to them.
Like you're breathing and then you concentrate on it and it goes.
Yeah, so exactly. So there are types of things that could be
like this. This is important though because it introduces this idea, because
you know with שמואל's Shmuel statement that without הרגשה hargasha a woman
is not a נידה דאורייתא, niddah de-oraita, could like make say that
well no woman is a נידה דאורייתא niddah de-oraita nowadays because how
many women have this sensation during bleeding, you know? So which is
actually a fascinating point because as we said when we learn שמואל,
Shmuel, what שמואל's Shmuel law does is it turns the objectifying of
the woman, of the נידה, niddah, and it creates a subject, you
know, it makes her into a subject again and it locates a
critical criteria in her subjective reality, which is why you find that
the פוסקים poskim for the first time start, not the first time,
but whatever, start asking women a lot, you know, after the גמרא,
Gemara, what is this sensation, do you have this sensation, a lot
of times the women say I don't know what the heck you're
talking about, you know, and then it becomes a problem, so how
do we, how is a woman a נידה דאורייתא niddah de-oraita now
if it requires this sensation? And one of the ways to bridge
that gap is introducing this concept: Well, maybe it's הרגשה ולאו אדעתא,
argasha ve-lav adaitah, maybe they're having the sensation without realizing it. So
the whole thing is that it doesn't make it moot, but then
again, well because it sounds like it would if you said it
all the time, but you don't say it all the time because
then it makes שמואל's Shmuel leniencies moot. So they try to find
a balance of times when to make that argument and when not.
And basically they'll make that argument when a woman is really getting
her period, when it's obvious by the quantity of the flow, whatever,
that she's really getting her period. Nobody's about to say oh but
she's not a נידה דאורייתא niddah de-oraita because here she is, she's
bleeding profusely and she's getting her period but she's not having the
sensation. So in order to bridge that gap, we'll say oh, הרגשה
ולאו אדעתא. argasha ve-lav adaitah. But if it's just normal staining, then
we'll go back to שמואל's Shmuel rule and say no sensation, it's
a כתם. ketem. So this becomes a very interesting area in הלכה
halacha where שמואל Shmuel introduces this major new criteria of sensation. It
becomes a real problem how the rabbis are going to deal with
it if they don't have access to it and does it really
exist, whatever. And then it leads to a whole balancing act, and
one of the ways of trying to deal with that is this
concept of הרגשה ולאו אדעתא. argasha ve-lav adaitah. Right.
Okay, yeah, it makes work for everyone in the morning.
I understand. Other people will argue that nowadays women are less, nowadays
all of us, men and women combined, are less in touch with
our bodies and, you know, whatever, we live in an artificial light
and in an artificially structured day and so on and in a
society more divorced from our physical sort of reality, so that maybe
certain sort of experiences are less accessible to us. Though.
Yeah, the way you frame this, it's always this kind of trying
to shoehorn reality into some kind of rigid categories of an abstract.
Yeah.
That is what happens. שמואל Shmuel introduces these categories, then people go
look and say what does this connect to? So, you know, maybe
the first approach is to try to connect it to realities that
we actually know occur, like maybe it's menstrual cramping. But the problem
is menstrual cramping does not always happen at the moment of the
bleeding itself. Maybe it precedes it or whatever. So there's a whole
problem about trying to, right, bridge that gap. And so you're exactly
right, that's what happens. Because שמואל Shmuel introduces this definition which we
don't have good access to.
Yeah. How שמואל, Shmuel, where did שמואל Shmuel learn it from?
Yes, that I have no idea. He makes his own דרשה drasha
from פסוקים. pesukim. I have no idea sort of where that came
out of.
He just said look, here's this, I'm going to tell you what's
going on here, there's this new criteria called הרגשה. hargasha. It's really
quite radical and it has profound impact. I will tell you, I
said yesterday, I'm going to say it again, but the profound impact
it has is before שמואל, Shmuel, if something was to be categorized
as a כתם, ketem, and let me just say right now what
are some of the leniencies about a כתם? ketem? Besides if you
can attribute it elsewhere then it's not טמא. tamei. But as you
might know, those is that if a stain is not that a
woman sees through her בדיקה bedika cloth and she knows it's coming
directly and sort of experiences it directly from her body, but she
finds a stain on her underwear or something like that, if it's
not on a white garment, if it's smaller than a certain size,
let's say it's the size of a גריס, gris, like a penny,
a nickel, whatever that size is, then you know
then or if it's not on something that can become that's מקבל
טומאה, mekabel tumah, which is a subcategory, then it's not a problem.
It's just a stain. Okay? So what that means though is, but
if a woman does an internal בדיקה bedika and it's a tiny
little dot, doesn't matter, there's no minimum size. So nowadays a woman
who finds a stain on her underwear will say oh it's just
a כתם, ketem, it's just a stain, it's not bigger than a
particular size, it's fine. That's all because of שמואל. Shmuel. Without שמואל,
Shmuel, we would have said it's not a כתם, ketem, it definitely
came from her body, it's tight-fitting underwear, how could you say otherwise?
Or she finds a stain on the toilet paper. And we'll say,
oh, well, the toilet paper, is it מקבל טומאה? mekabel tumah? Or
it's disposable, it's not even whatever cloth, or it's colored toilet paper,
don't worry about it, it's just a stain. And when we haven't
seen it yet, we'll see it. Okay, it's just a stain. What
do you mean it's just a stain? It's definitely from her body.
So what allows us to define these things as stains and a
lot of the practical leniencies nowadays of stains and הלכות נדה hilchos
niddah is because of שמואל. Shmuel. שמואל Shmuel says even if it's
definitely from her body, there's this new criteria called הרגשה. hargasha. But
the problem is that then we don't know what the הרגשה hargasha
is talking about, so we sort of find it as תוספות Tosfos
says shoehorned back in when we know a woman's really having her
period. When she's really having her period, then we'll assume she's getting
a הרגשה hargasha and she doesn't, it's just a way to work
it.
Yes, but I don't understand how the concept of הרגשה hargasha allows
a leniency of stains.
Because then we could say even when it's definitely from her body,
at the absence of הרגשה, hargasha, it is not a biblical נדה
niddah and it's just the rabbinic category of stains. But שמואל Shmuel
basically says the dividing line between what we call ראיה, reiah, really
seeing blood, and stains is not that stains is that there's an
element of doubt, it's that stains are not accompanied with a הרגשה.
hargasha.
So he's putting all of the diagnostic imperative on the woman.
Yeah, in terms of whether there's a הרגשה hargasha or not. Correct.
Okay, so we and that is still true today?
Well, no, because because I mean it might have been it might
it might have been if the, you know, if if there was
if we could identify this reality of הרגשה, hargasha, meaning if women
would say, "Yeah, yeah, some of the times I do have this
sensation when I'm bleeding, I didn't have it today," then I assume
that actually הלכה halacha would be more ask women whether they're getting
that sensation or not, you know. But the problem is that and
is that, you know, you do find no, no, after the גמרא,
Gemara, you have hundreds of years of rabbis trying to figure out
what this הרגשה hargasha is and inquiring women from women and getting
responses that didn't fit what the גמרא Gemara said and sort of
having being frustrated and throwing up their hands a little bit. So
I mean that's I mean this is what it does because it
relocates it into women's domain and then the rabbis are trying to
connect that to, you know, to the פסק psak and having a
real hard time because what women are reporting is not what the
גמרא Gemara is saying. So, yeah.
Yeah, I have a stylistic question. Yes. This ברייתא, braita, תא שמע,
tashma, where does it begin, where does it end? It ends in
the middle.
תא שמע נמצאת אתה אומר. tashma nimetzeita omer.
Yeah, I don't
know, referring to something that's not there.
Right. It might be a תוספתא tosefta going on. Yeah.
And where does it end?
Well, it ends with הלכה כהרוב. halacha k'harov.
And מאי mai is the גמרא Gemara inquisitive. But yeah, I don't
know what the context is.
Is it in ברייתא braita language?
No, sometimes it is, but you're right, it's in the middle of
a larger discussion and we don't know where the I don't know
what the larger discussion is. Okay, one last one and then yeah.
Because you mentioned, you know, let's say it's on a toilet paper,
whatever it is, but you know, we also said that if she's
going to the bathroom, maybe because the sensation of so how does
that get incorporated?
So that's a question. Are we more strict if we
are we more strict if a woman finds a stain on toilet
paper? On the one hand we use שמואל Shmuel to say even
though it's definitely from her body, it's a כתם. kesem. On the
other hand, some people say, "Ah, but according to this גמרא, Gemara,
maybe the sensation of urination is confused with the sensation of this
הרגשה." hargasha. In this גמרא Gemara though you set it as a
leniency, even though there's a sensation, you don't have to assume that
it is the problematic sensation. But could we be using that as
a stringency? So that is some of the discussion. Some people there's
a big debate of the פוסקים. poskim. Some פוסקים poskim are much
more strict with stains on toilet paper because of the of the
sensation of urination and others are not. Others say that that's not
what the גמרא Gemara is talking about.
Does it say anything about the ברייתא braita whether she's sitting or
standing?
No. Okay, so anyway, so now you are really seeing a lot
of this גמרא Gemara right now is the source of exactly figuring
out what category to put stains in, in particular when we know
it the woman knows it's coming from her body. So anyway, the
גמרא Gemara now introduced this idea, "Well, maybe she had a sensation
she doesn't know." Of course תוספות Tosafot says, once you're introducing this
idea, maybe she had a sensation she's not aware of, it makes
שמואל's Shmuel whole הלכה halacha moot because then all the time maybe
she had a sensation she's not aware of. What's the point of
saying there's a criteria of sensation? So תוספות Tosafot says we're just
introducing it in this one case where she found a stain on
her garment and it's an old stain and she has no idea
when it came from. So then we're talking about a possible long
period of time. So there we can say maybe in the last
two weeks whenever this stain came on, you know, she wasn't aware
of it. But if it's a recent thing, שמואל's Shmuel statement still
is meaningful because if she recently, you know, had some saw a
stain and there was no sensation, according to שמואל Shmuel it would
still not be נדה דאורייתא. niddah d'oraisa. So now the גמרא Gemara
is going to continue. Let's continue with let's see where it goes
next.
So it says like
this, אמר מר, amar mar,
על בשרה, al besarah, now let's get back now let's go go
back to look at this ברייתא. braita. על בשרה, al besarah, if
it's on her body itself, ספק טמא ספק טהור טמא. safek tamei
safek tahor tamei. If you don't know whether it's from her or
not, whether it's טמא tamei or טהור, tahor, you assume it's from
her and she's טמא. tamei. על חלוקה, al chalukah, on her garment,
ספק טמא ספק טהור טהור. safek tamei safek tahor tahor. If you
don't know where it's from, then you assume it's from elsewhere. היכי
דמי, heichi dami, what's the case? אי מחגור ולמטה, ei mechagor l'matah,
first I'll try to figure out. First I'll try to figure this
out in context of our משנה. mishna. Our משנה mishna says didn't
say that we're more strict by body than by clothes, our משנה
mishna just said where on the body, where on the clothes, and
this ברייתא beraita says there's a difference between body and clothes. Let's
try to fit those two together. אי מחגור ולמטה, ei mehachagor u'lemata,
if it's below the belt, על חלוקה, al chaluka, אמאי טהור? amai
tahor? Why are you making saying it's okay if it's on her
garment? Our משנה mishna says below the belt even on the garment
is no good. והתנן, vehatnan, מן החגור ולמטה, min hachagor u'lemata, טמא.
tamei. From the belt and below is טמא tamei even on the
garment. ואי מחגור ולמעלה, ve'ei mehachagor u'lemala, if it is above the
belt area, then על בשרה, al basara, אמאי טמאה? amai tmeia? Then
even if it's on her flesh why should she be טמאה? tmeia?
והתנן, vehatnan, our משנה mishna says ראתה דם על בשרה, ra'ata dam
al basara, if she sees it on her flesh, שלא כנגד בית
התורפה, shelo k'neged beit haturpa, not in the genital area, טהורה היא,
tehora hi, she's טהורה. tehora. So basically it's saying our משנה mishna
distinguishes between between where on the body and or where on the
garment. It doesn't make a difference between body versus garment, whereas this
ברייתא beraita does. So how do you reconcile those two? So the
גמרא gemara says אי בעית אימא מחגור ולמטה אי בעית אימא מחגור
ולמעלה. ei ba'it eima mehachagor u'lemata ei ba'it eima mehachagor u'lemala. I
can read this ברייתא beraita either when it's above the belt or
below the belt and say that it does sometimes matter body versus
clothes. Let's take a look, and either below the belt or above.
אי בעית אימא מחגור ולמטה, ei ba'it eima mehachagor u'lemata, here's how
I could read it below the belt. כגון שעברה בשוק של טבחים.
kegon she'avra beshuk shel tabachim. There's a reason to assume it came
from elsewhere. It's below the belt which normally would be problematic, but
you have counterbalancing that the fact that she walked into the butcher
place in the marketplace. Now this is not your clean antiseptic butcher
store that we go into, right? This is blood flying all over
the place, right? Like walking into the שוק shuk whatever, except imagine
that they've got, you know, killing animals and and whatever, all that
stuff flying around. So, she does have it on her below her
belt, but there's something else that could be the cause of it.
So then we start to ask, oh well then where is it?
Is it on her clothes or is it on her body? על
בשרה, al basara, if it's on her body, מגופא אתי, migupha ati,
then you have to assume it's still from her, it's still from
her even though she went through the butcher area. Why? דאי מעלמא
אתי, de'ei me'alma ati, because if it was from the butchers, then
על חלוקה מבעי ליה אשתכוחי. al chaluka mibei lei ishtakuchi. Then you
wouldn't just have found it on her body, it would have found
it on her clothes too. How does it get all the way
to her skin without first getting on her clothes? So if it's
coming from the outside, if there's a reason to say it came
from the outside, then you cannot use that as an excuse if
it's just on her skin without also being on her clothes.
Even when they were completely covered? Yes, as it says, what is
it, a קופא kuppa that they were wearing.
No, but it's by the way on her skin doesn't mean all
places on her skin. On her skin just means on her skin...
on her leg?
Right, on her leg where there's direct access where blood could directly
drop.
Yeah, but still they're assuming in
that that she's
got clothing.
Right, that's a good point, presumably, right? Presumably.
You'd never have to say that you could say that it's a
case where she's wearing a long dress.
Right. If it's on her skin which was exposed, then this wouldn't
be, but it's right, that's the other point. It could just be
talking about skin that is... skin that is under her clothes. Okay,
anyway, על חלוקה, al chaluka, if it's on her garment, מעלמא אתי,
me'alma ati, then you could be lenient and say it came from
the butchers. דאי מגופא אתי, de'ei migupha ati, because if it came
from her body, על בשרה מבעי ליה אשתכוחי, al basara mibei lei
ishtakuchi, then it wouldn't have just gotten on her garment, it would
have also been on her body as well. Now, we won't... that's
a little superfluous because you don't need that kind of... you don't
need that sort of additional supporting evidence. Once she's going through a
marketplace and it's on her garment, that's enough. Okay, but the real
point is that the marketplace, the butcher place is not enough if
it's just on her
skin because then the question is, well why isn't it on her
garment as well?
Well, if it's on her skin and her garment?
Right, then it would be, then it would be. ואי בעית אימא,
ve'ei ba'it eima, if you want you could say, right, that's the
problem, that this thing is inconsistent. What if it's on both? The
first half makes it sound okay, the second not good. Presumably then
actually it is okay. ואי בעית אימא, ve'ei ba'it eima, if you
want you could say מחגור ולמעלה, mehachagor u'lemala, that it's above the
belt. וכגון דאיסטרקא, u'kegon de'istarka, and she was doing calisthenics. על בשרה,
al basara, אמאי, amai, מגופא אתי. migupha ati.
So then if it's on her flesh, it's from her body. דאי
מעלמא אתי, de'ei me'alma ati, again the argument being
that if it was from elsewhere, על חלוקה איבעי ליה אשתכוחי, al
chaluka ibei lei ishtakuchi, then it would have been on her garment.
Because, you know, how'd it get on her flesh without getting on
her garment? So we understand why it's above the belt, she was
doing calisthenics, but we can't understand why it's on her flesh and
not on her garment. On one minute... על חלוקה, al chaluka, if
it's on her garment, then even though she didn't go through a
marketplace, the fact that it's above the belt, then we'll be...
we'll say that it's not from her, even though she did calisthenics.
We'll say מעלמא אתי, me'alma ati, it still came from elsewhere. דאי
מגופא אתי, de'ei migupha ati, because if it came from her body,
על בשרה איבעי ליה אשתכוחי, al basara ibei lei ishtakuchi, then it
should have also been on her flesh. Now, of course as Michael
sort of indicated, there's a little bit of what's unclear here is
what do you do in a case when it's both on her
flesh and on her garment? In that way are you willing to...
meaning on her garment? On her flesh and on her garment. Are
you then you're willing to say it came from the outside and
hit both? Or saying it came from her body and it hit
both? Anyway, so that's not clear from this, but the key point
of this structure is is that we look at multiple factors to
determine if there's an element of doubt where it came from. Okay,
one factor is our משנה mishna talks about where on the body,
where on the garment it is. Below the belt obviously is one
thing, above the belt is another. Another factor is particularly if it's
just on the body without being on the garment, you know, so
another factor is like how did it get on the body without...
getting on the
garment. And so that question about being on the body versus being
on the garment or only one without the other is another factor
that will indicate to us whether it came from the outside or
whether it came from her. And we sort of, all of those
things go into an equation to determine what her status
is based on also other factors. Is she doing calisthenics? Is she
walking through a marketplace with butchers? So all those things we look
at the various factors of above the belt, below the belt, body,
skin, body, clothes, etc.
Yes, of our, well, what
we made, we're not up to yet, hold on, we'll consider whether
the crust
is in the blood, whether it came from the outside versus inside,
that kind
of thing.
So maybe, and there's a lot of the laws of כתמים ketamim
which are looking at the circumstance and trying to
determine like what can we what can we infer here for the
likelihood that it came from elsewhere. The basic principle is, let me
simplify it. You don't need evidence
that it came from elsewhere, you just need a good ability to
say it's possible it came from elsewhere. If you have a good
ability to say, oh, he walked through the marketplace, the butcher place,
we can say it's from there and it's not like it's absurd
because it's not like it's on her skin without being on her
garments, then you can say it's from the marketplace. If it's on
a place, if you don't know where it came from, but there's
no logic how it got there from her bleeding, like it's above
the belt, then fine, even without knowing where it came from, we
assume it's not from her. As long as there's basically a good
argument to say it came from elsewhere, we are lenient and that's
one of the leniencies of כתמים ketamim we're going to continue to
look at that. Let's just hold off the questions, I just want
to bring this to a conclusion and then we'll take other questions.
So let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. דתני מיהא, De-tani
miha,
now let's get to Michael's point. We taught nonetheless, על בשרה ספק
טמא ספק טהור טמא. al besara safek tamei safek tahor tamei. If
it's on her flesh under certain circumstances, we'll be inclined to say
it is טמא. tamei. ואף על גב דלא הרגישה, Ve-af al gav
de-lo hirgisha,
even though there's no הרגשה, hargasha, right? Again, there's cases of doubt,
there's no הרגשה. hargasha. This is not a case like תוספות Tosafot
said it's been a long time, so maybe in the last two
weeks I had הרגשה. hargasha. Right now recently I found something on
the flesh, on my flesh. So again, no הרגשה, hargasha, and she's
still טמאה. tmeah. ותנן, Ve-tnan, and what about all the laws of
כתמים? ketamim? Stains, it's not about הרגשה. hargasha. הרואה כתם על בשרה,
Ha-roah ketem al besara, if a woman sees a stain on her
flesh, כנגד בית התורפה, keneged beit ha-turpa, opposite the genital area, טמאה,
tmeah, she's טמאה. tmeah. ואף על גב דלא הרגישה, Ve-af al gav
de-lo hirgisha, no הרגשה. hargasha. So basically what does שמואל Shmuel mean
she's not טמאה? tmeah? We have all the laws of כתמים ketamim
which never mention הרגשה. hargasha. Now I already told you what the
answer is going to be, but let's take a look what the
גמרא Gemara said, because there's a difference between biblical and rabbinic. But
the גמרא Gemara thinks that שמואל Shmuel is trying to say she's
טהור tahor completely. ואמר רב ירמיה מדפתי מודה שמואל שהיא טמאה מדרבנן.
Ve-amar Rav Yirmiyah mi-Difti modeh Shmuel she-hi tmeah mi-derabbanan. Yes, of course,
שמואל Shmuel agrees that there's a rabbinic category called stains that doesn't
require הרגשה. hargasha. What שמואל Shmuel meant was that she's not a
biblical נדה. niddah. Now you'll say who cares? She's a נדה, niddah,
who cares whether it's one or the other? Well I told you,
there's a huge difference. If it's stains, there are a lot of
leniencies. A, if there's an argument to attribute it elsewhere, we'll use
that argument. B, if it's smaller than a certain size, it's not
a problem. C, if it's not on a white garment, it's not
a problem, etc. etc. So there's a lot of leniencies when we
put it in this rabbinic category and then we apply those even
today. And therefore שמואל Shmuel is admitting it's a stain, but he's
saying she's not a נדה דאורייתא. niddah de-oraita. That's his answer. רב
אשי אמר, Rav Ashi amar, רב אשי Rav Ashi says, שמואל הוא
דאמר כרבי נחמיה. Shmuel hu de-amar ke-Rabbi Nechemiah. He's going like
רבי נחמיה. Rabbi Nechemiah. דתניא במשנה, De-tanya ba-mishnah,
רבי נחמיה אומר כל דבר שאינו מקבל טומאה אינו מקבל כתמים. Rabbi
Nechemiah omer kol davar she-eino mekabbol tumah eino mekabbol ketamim. And this
is another one of the leniencies of stains, if it's on something
that is not, cannot become טמא. tamei. What is an example of
that? Well toilet paper's an example of that. Toilet paper is A,
disposable things might in general not be able to become טמא. tamei.
And B, more important, toilet paper whatever because it's not like a
כלי. kli. Number two is toilet paper is not like a woven
garment. The types of things that are sort of cloths, woven garments
are טמא. tamei. Something which was basically just like pressed paper or
whatever is not. So if it's not on something that can become
טמא, tamei, then there's not a problem of stains. I'll tell you
why in a minute. But how does this answer it? Because remember
שמואל Shmuel's case was that she saw it on the hard ground.
Well ground, earth cannot become טומאה. tumah. So basically תוספות Tosafot reads
this as that he's agreeing with what we said before. שמואל Shmuel
agrees to a category of כתמים ketamim of rabbinic
stains without הרגשה. hargasha. But in שמואל Shmuel's one case of sitting
on the ground, he was able to say טהור tahor completely because
that was a case which wouldn't even be in this rabbinic category
of stains because it's something that cannot become
טמא. tamei. Wait let's just finish. So the גמרא Gemara says, בשלמא
לרב אשי היינו דקאמר קרקע. bishlama le-Rav Ashi hainu de-ka'amar karka. So
according to רב אשי, Rav Ashi, we understand why שמואל Shmuel gave
the example of sitting on the ground because he wanted to give
an example where she was totally טהור. tahor. אלא לרב ירמיה מאי
איריא קרקע? Ella le-Rav Yirmiyah mai irya karka? According to רב ירמיה,
Rav Yirmiyah, why did שמואל Shmuel give this example of sitting on
the ground? אפילו גלימא נמי, Afillu glima nami, שמואל Shmuel could have
said if she sits on a garment then she's not a נדה
דאורייתא niddah de-oraita but she's still rabbinically it's a stain. Why give
the example of the ground? So לא מיבעיא קאמר, lo miba'ya ka'amar,
it goes without saying. לא מיבעיא גלימא דלא מיבדקא שפיר, Lo miba'ya
glima de-lo mibdika shapir, if it was a garment you would have
said, yeah, you know why that's just a stain? Because you didn't
check the garment well. If it was a garment you would have
check the garment fully, you know, things can get hidden in the
garment and maybe the stain was there from
beforehand ואיכא למימר מעלמא, ve'ika lemeimar me'alma, so maybe it came from
elsewhere, then you wouldn't have been impressed with Shmuel's ruling, you would
have said she's not a נדה דאורייתא niddah de-oraita for the normal
reason of stains. You don't know it came from her. אלא אפילו
קרקע, ella afillu karka, but even if it's right on the ground
and it's tough and it's flat, it's hard, there are no folds,
you you know how hard is it to check a square, you
know, foot of ground? And ואיכא למימר מגופא אתיא ve'ika lemeimar migufa
atya and there presumably it came from her body, nevertheless טהורה, tehorah,
nevertheless she's okay because there was no הרגשה. hargasha. Now the way
I read the conclusion of the גמרא, Gemara, we conclude with saying,
okay, Shmuel, we got you, without הרגשה hargasha it's only rabbinic, it's
in this rabbinic category of כתמים. ketamim. That won't apply with regards
to מקבל טומאה, mekabel tumah, other stains- places, but there are leniencies
when it's in that category, but without הרגשה hargasha we can put
it in that category, and that as I said the biggest relevance
is a woman finds a stain which no question came from her
body, on tight-fitting underwear, on toilet paper, and we can still thanks
to Shmuel put it in this category of כתמים ketamim and apply
the leniencies of שיעור shiur and size, etc. because there's no הרגשה.
hargasha.
Right, even if it's a day before her period?
Yes, although that raises interesting- yes, a day before period yes, if
it's on the time she's expecting her period it gets a little
bit more iffy, but basically yes. Okay, and this allows for a
lot of leniencies. Now I want to say a couple of- I
want to say a couple of concluding
things about this. Number one, let's first do the simple thing which
we'll get back to. Why does the whole law of כתמים ketamim
only apply on things that are מקבל טומאה? mekabel tumah? So, as
you might have been aware, we introduced the- I'll tell you what
תוספות Tosafot says, which is pretty much universally assumed. We introduced the
whole story of כתמים ketamim not about the question about נדה niddah
nowadays and can a woman have sex with her husband and so
on. We introduce the whole discussion about if you're finding stains and
you touch it and somebody else touches it, you know, טומאה וטהרה
tumah ve-taharah and eating תרומה, terumah, a whole world where there's all
those concerns of טומאה וטהרה tumah ve-taharah and not even so much
about the woman's status alone but about generally other people's טומאה וטהרה
tumah ve-taharah and so on. So תוספות Tosafot says you know the
whole category of כתמים ketamim being טמא tamei was started in the
world of טומאה וטהרה. tumah ve-taharah. It didn't start in the world
of contemporary הלכות נדה. hilchos niddah. Once the rabbis decided that נדה
niddah stains, you know, stains on garments that are most likely from
when a woman was menstruating are going to be טמא, tamei, then
they said well we can't make the stains טמא tamei without making
the woman טמאה, temeiah, so because obviously that would be inconsistent, so
then they decided the woman would be טמאה temeiah as well within
this rabbinic category of כתמים. ketamim. But if we can't start by
making the stains טמא, tamei, then we also will not make the
woman טמאה. temeiah. And therefore if it's not on something that's מקבל
טומאה, mekabel tumah, so the whole thing becomes like moot, it starts
there, then the woman will not be טמאה temeiah as well. That's
תוספות's Tosafot argument which is fascinating, which basically says this entire category
of כתמים ketamim which is a big part of contemporary הלכות נדה
hilchos niddah really started and is anchored in a world that was
not about the woman's status but the world of טומאה וטהרה tumah
ve-taharah which for the most part we've assumed we've left behind, like
the two daily checks and all that other type of stuff. I
should also mention interestingly parenthetically that the רי"ף Rif doesn't bring down
any discussion about stains, so of
כתמים. ketamim. So some ראשונים Rishonim speculate that maybe the רי"ף Rif
thought no הלכות כתמים hilchos ketamim were relevant nowadays. Which would be
מיקל, meikel, that because it's rooted in the world of טומאה וטהרה
tumah ve-taharah that even as it applies to
the woman's status is only when we're dealing with טומאה וטהרה, tumah
ve-taharah, so not nowadays. But, you know, none of the ראשונים Rishonim
say that, all the ראשונים Rishonim פוסקין pasken these הלכות halachos of
כתמים. ketamim. But that is interesting. Point number two is
because גמרא Gemara ends by saying that when she sits on קרקע,
karka, איכא למימר מגופא אתיא, ve'ika lemeimar migufa atya, not it- could
have said ודאי מגופא אתיא, vada'ei migufa atya, it's definitely from her
body and nevertheless she's טהורה, tehorah, it says איכא למימר, ve'ika lemeimar,
it's possible that it's most likely from her body. Some want to
say that even in the conclusion that Shmuel's הלכה halacha about sensation
הרגשה hargasha is not a per se criteria. His הלכה halacha about
הרגשה hargasha is as an indicator that it came from the body.
That when there's a little element of doubt, so the lack of
הרגשה hargasha tells you it didn't come from the body. But that
they would argue, there are some אחרונים Acharonim who want to argue
that when it's 100% from the woman's body, like this tight-fitting underwear,
then then forget Shmuel's requirement of הרגשה. hargasha. That his הרגשה hargasha
is still feeding into the general idea that כתמים ketamim have an
element of doubt. And they base it on the fact that the
גמרא Gemara doesn't end by saying ודאי מגופא אתיא, vada'ei migufa atya,
it says איכא למימר מגופא אתיא. ve'ika lemeimar migufa atya. So there
still is some אחרונים Acharonim that are- do not want to take
Shmuel's position to the end point, but generally as a rule we
do. And again as I said, the problem becomes if women say
nowadays they don't get this sensation at all, so do we basically
say that no women are נדה דאורייתא niddah de-oraita nowadays? And, you
know, how do we try to bridge the gap about reality and
the halachic issues and I said that's using some of the what
the גמרא Gemara said earlier of הרגשה ולאו אדעתה hargasha ve-lav ada'atah
try to be the way in which that gap is closed. But
this is a very major area in practical הלכות נדה hilchos niddah
and I just wanted to highlight some of the relevant aspects.
Yes, so maybe there's another
point of
view,
another thing going on with Shmuel, another's that... Right but I
mean to say
right but he's not denying I understand he's not formalizing he's not
rejecting those non-formalistic
measures right? He agrees that those non-formalistic measures will also get you
out of the problem he's introducing yet another measure that will get
you out of it so yeah I don't see yeah I see
I just yeah I don't see.
During these times were women supposed to come to a rabbi every
time they saw a stain on their garments?
Well we don't know we definitely have some reports that they did.
How much was assumed that they likely did or how much was
assumed that they could have figured those things out for themselves and
knew the rules for themselves is never made exactly clear. Like nowadays
there are women who come all the time and there are women
who
learn the parameters and make decisions for themselves and then I'm sure
there are people who can't be bothered one way or the other
way so.
Some of the rabbis see stains on their garments?
Yeah we're about to see that in the משנה Mishnah coming up.
Nowadays? Absolutely. That's what a major impetus a major impetus a major
impetus for of women to go to rabbis and
a major impetus for the Orthodox world. This is the first you're
hearing about this?
Of course it is. A major impetus for the reason that they
did יועצות הלכה נדה Yoatzot Halacha Niddah was so that women could
go to other women. And now there are some rabbis before that
and even till today who sort of do it more like anonymously
like you drop something off with whatever or you get your husband
to ask for you but yeah that was a I
understand שמואל Shmuel moving as that there is definitely הרגשה hargashah but
not when it comes potentially to very small amounts
and maybe what he's trying to say is don't worry about a
small amount.
Well that goes back to that goes back to the point I
said before that when there's a real profuse bleeding we're going to
sort of say that the presence of or we're going to assume
הרגשה hargashah and that that's why nobody will say that if a
woman is like heavily staining and she's wearing a pad oh there's
no הרגשה hargashah it's only a
כתם.
ketam. But the כתם ketam is because you
find something and then deduce that something happened without feeling and maybe
what he's ruling here is to not count it unless you have
a sensation.
I understand I understand so but fine so yes but I'm just
saying I think that that line about quantity is drawn but maybe
a little bit more leniently than you're drawing it. Not like a
tiny little dot but a line which is if there's a lot
of bleeding that's clear she's getting her period then we're not going
to use שמואל's Shmuel ruling but if it's but what you're saying
is if it's a tiny little dot anyway whatever but yes there
is that idea. But quick two very quick things because we have
to move on.
The first point the משנה Mishnah spoke about was out of the
world of נדה Niddah and into the world of טומאה וטהרה tumah
ve-taharah and therefore the stain made the woman טמאה. tmeiah.
Point says is that we started with stains in the world of
טומאה וטהרה tumah ve-taharah and then to be consistent we had to
make the woman טמאה tmeiah as well but if
she's not a נדה Niddah she's just טמאה? tmeiah?
No no as a נדה Niddah as a נדה Niddah okay.
Yeah no
I was going to see the same thing because he's ruling from
טומאה וטהרה tumah ve-taharah we're saying it's a big actually חומרא chumra
that we're doing now. Sure. Because because שמואל Shmuel was saying nothing
in terms of whether she's permitted or prohibited vis-a-vis her husband. Right.
And we're saying that one will imply the other
right that
if she's טמאה tmeiah then she's a נדה Niddah and if she's
a נדה Niddah then she's אסורה asurah to her husband.
Yes. And that's clear I mean the גמרא Gemara never has had
a woman being טמאה נדה tmeiah Niddah without being I mean it's
had some requirement that she had to do in a world of
טומאה וטהרה tumah ve-taharah but if once it's ruling that she's a
נדה Niddah then she's אסורה asurah to her husband.
I have one question. Yes. Do they also teach this part to
look at stains to assume that they communicate?
Well we hope that they'll work
with יועצות הלכה Yoatzot Halacha and so on and we bring them
in when we learn הלכות נדה Hilchos Niddah but we also that's
not always available and so we also do training of looking at
stains. We do that.
And are women encouraged to do this?
Bring the stains to the rabbi? Well either to do that or
assume they're טמאה tmeiah so if they want to I mean you've
got two options if you're not asking the rabbi you'll just assume
it's okay or you'll assume it's not good either you're being too
lenient or too strict you know so but I've never
heard of a rabbi who complained that more women should know.
All right let's we have to move on. Okay. עלה כפה על
ראש כל
אצבע טמאה.
aleh kapa al rosh kol etzba
tmeiah. Okay. Look, let's try, let's try to get a little bit
further today. על עקבה דעל ראש קוצתא דצמהא. al ikva d'al rosh
kutzta d'tzameha. בשלמא bishlama עקבה ikva on her, on her, on her
heel, then it's טמאה. temeah. עביד דנגע בההוא מקום, avid d'naga b'hahu
makom, it's possible you could, you know, sit, whatever that's called, cross-legged
and the heel could touch the pubic area. אלא ראש גודלה מאי
טעמא? ela rosh godla mai taama? How does it get on her
toe? If it's, it's assuming that it's coming through direct touch. וכי
תימא זימנין דנגעה בעקבה? ve'chi teima zimnin d'nagah b'ikva? Maybe her toe
touches her heel. ומי מחזקינן טומאה ממקום למקום? u'mi machzikinan tumah mi'makom
l'makom? But you're not,
as I told you in yesterday, is that we will only assume
that it's a problem if it could have gotten there directly, not
indirectly. דתניא, d'tanya, we taught in the ברייתא, braita, היתה לה מכה
בצוארה, haita lah maka b'tzavarah, she has a
wound on her neck. שתכול לתלות she'tuchal litlos and she could say,
oh yeah, the reason I got the stain on my thigh is
because you know, maybe it dripped from my neck. So in that
case תולת. toles. So this is the general rule as I told
you, which is that if there's a way to make it to,
to attribute it to an external source, we do. אף כתפה, af
ktefah, now if it's on her back shoulder, שאינה יכולה לתלות, she'eina
yechola litlos, there's no way it got from the shoulder to her
thigh, so אינה תולת. eina toles. She can't say, oh it came,
the blood came from my shoulder. ואין אומרים, v'ein omrim, you do
not say, oh there is a way, שמא בידה נטלה והביאה לשם,
shema b'yadah natlah v'hevi'ah l'sham, maybe she touched her wound on her
back shoulder and then she touched her thigh. You don't say that.
So you see that you do not use to be lenient to
say, oh it came from another source indirectly. And the גמרא Gemara
is saying the same way you don't use to be lenient indirect,
we're not going to use it to be strict either.
So if it, how did it get on her toe? You can't
say it got to her toe via her heel. We're not going
to say that to be lenient or to be strict, only if
it's direct. Why not? אלא ela because, because these are formal rules.
אלא שאני ראש גודלה דבהדי דפסעה עביד דמירמי, ela shani rosh godla
d'bahadei d'pasa avid d'mirmi, so that her toe is different because as
she's walking it is possible that sometimes it is directly underneath, you
know, her, you know, right, you know, between her thighs and her
pubic area. So it is possible that not that her toe touched
the area but that it fell directly from that onto her toe.
So now the גמרא Gemara says, ולא מחזקינן טומאה ממקום למקום? v'lo
machzikinan tumah mi'makom l'makom? Are you telling me we're not going to
assume that it came from one place to another? Meaning we're not
going to be concerned about indirect transfer. והתניא, v'hatanya, we taught in
the ברייתא, braita, נמצאת על קשרי אצבעותיה, nimtzet al kishrei etzbe'oteha, if
she finds blood on her like, you know, on her knuckles, טמאה
מפני שידיה עסקניות הן. temeah mipnei she'yadeha askaniyot hen. She's טמאה temeah
because you can assume that your hands are touching all places, you're
not paying attention, so maybe she touched, you know, directly her pubic
area. So the גמרא Gemara says, מאי טעמא? mai taama? What's the
reason?
דאמרינן בדקה בחד ידא ונגע באידך ידא. d'amrinan badkah b'chad yada v'naga
b'idach yada. So the גמרא Gemara assumes it's not stam like her
whole hand is there. Maybe she checked with one, you know, with
her finger, checked the area and then accidentally that finger touched her,
you know, the knuckles on the other hand. So you see we're
concerned here indirectly. So the גמרא Gemara says,
לא, שאני יד דכולה עבידא דנגע. lo, shani yad d'kula avida d'naga.
Who knows? Your whole hand could have directly touched, you know, and
you're not paying attention and whatever and it could be on all
of your knuckles and it's not indirect, it could be direct. So
this is an important principle that A, to assume she's טמאה temeah
it'd have to be able to have gotten there directly. B, if
we want to be lenient and say it came from an external
source, we also have to say that it came from the external
source directly.
ולא מחזקינן טומאה ממקום למקום ולא מחזקינן טהרה ממקום למקום. v'lo machzikinan
tumah mi'makom l'makom v'lo machzikinan taharah mi'makom l'makom. You do not use
indirect, it has to be direct. Okay, so now moving on. על
שוקה ועל פרסותיה מבפנים, al shokah v'al parsoteiha mi'bifnim, if it's on
her calves and on her inner instep. Is that what you call
it, the inner instep? What do you call this piece on
the... instep. The instep. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says, מבפנים עד
היכא? mi'bifnim ad heicha? How, until when in terms of on, you
know, on the inside is it a problem? So אמר דבי רבי
ינאי עד מקום חבק, amar d'bei Rabbi Yannai ad makom chavack, until
the place of חבק, chavack, which might mean joining or whatever. This
is hamstring.
מקום חבק makom chavack is hamstring. Okay, fine. I'm translating חבק. chavack.
So you're telling me
hamstring in... What's the
hamstring? רש"י Rashi says, בחבק bachavack is basically the sinews, the area
that connects the, the leg to the thigh. Is that the hamstring?
Hamstring is the muscle behind it.
The hamstring is this, all the way down here? Okay, so that's
funny that they translated that because שוק shok is the, is the
calf. So here we said... So רש"י Rashi anyway says that it's
this area around the knee that combines the, combines the calf with
the thigh.
Is the hamstring over here? It's behind the knee.
Is it behind the knee? Okay. I don't know. רש"י Rashi says
basically it's the area behind the knee. Now that's a little bit
funny because the גמרא Gemara here is, you know, the משנה Mishna
is discussing is it on the inside or the outside, but the
גמרא Gemara seems to be asking the question about like also lengthwise.
How far down do we still consider it to be? And it
says till this area of the whatever, of the hamstring or of
the knee area and so on. So איבעיא להו, iba'ya l'hu, מקום
חבק כבפנים או כבחוץ? makom chavack k'vifnim o k'vachutz? But again... it
sounds like it's more talking about defining inside versus outside rather than
height, so I have to tell you I’m not, it’s not exactly
clear to me, sort of, you know, how the גמרא Gemara is
interpreting this משנה, Mishnah, you know, whether it’s trying to say I
get the inside idea, but where height on the leg, or is
it trying to define this as what inside means, and I don’t
and I don’t exactly get it. Anyway, is the place of the
חבק, chavok, is it like the inside or the outside? תא שמע
Ta shma דתני detani רב קטינא: Rav Katina: עד מקום חבק, ad
mekom chavok, until the place of חבק, chavok, וחבק עצמו כלפנים, vachavok
atzmo kelifnim, and that itself counts as the inside.
רב פפא, Rav Pappa, רב חייא בריה דרב אוייא, Rav Chiya brei
deRav Avya, מתני לה בהדיא, matni lah behedya, אמרי דבי רבי ינאי:
amrei devei Rabbi Yannai: עד מקום חבק ad mekom chavok וחבק עצמו
כלפנים, vachavok atzmo kelifnim, and that counts as the inside. So whatever
is that location on the leg on the thigh. Now בעי רבי
ירמיה, Ba'ei Rabbi Yirmeyah, Rabbi Yirmeyah asks: כשיר מהו, kashir mahu, let’s
say there are dots on her leg on a place when normally
you would say that she is טמאה temeah on her thigh, that
is, however, they are sort of circular, they’re like little dots around
that make a circle. כשור מהו, kashur mahu, or let’s say they
make a line, they’re little dots in a line. טיפין טיפין מהו,
tipin tipin mahu, or just scattered dots like a scatter, you know,
scattergram, what’s it called, whatever anyway, so those types of things. Now
the question being on the one hand it’s in the area that
you should assume it’s from her, on the other hand it’s in
a configuration that it’s not natural, you would not normally assume that
if blood was dripping from her this is what it would look
like, splatter or whatever. So you know, what would it be?
I don’t know, it wouldn’t be the same, wouldn't be the same
thing also.
Yes, that’s a good point, right. How else did it get in
an interesting circular pattern? Right, I don’t know. But maybe we don’t
need the answer to that. Like when it’s on a part of
her body that it didn’t come from her, we don’t need to
explain where it came from, we just need a good argument that
it’s not from her. But you know Michael makes a good point,
but but you know, you don’t need to know where it came
from as long as it, sort of like in a court case,
you
know,
she stepped in a puddle of blood at the butcher shop and
splatter in a certain way, but it wouldn’t make a perfect circle.
A perfect circle would probably be from pressure from something that
had, oh that’s interesting, something better.
Ah,
okay.
Okay. Anyway the basic point is that if there’s a good argument
it’s not from her, we might not even really need to know
where it’s from, so that’s the question. So the גמרא Gemara says
like
this: לרוחב ירך מהו, lerochav yerech mahu, what if it’s a line
but it’s not going lengthwise, it’s going sort of widthwise, what’s the
story there? Okay, so what’s the story? So on her thigh. תא
שמע, Ta shma, come hear: על בשרה, al besarah, if it's on
the flesh, ספק טמא ספק טהור, safek tamei safek tahor, טמא. tamei.
So if we don’t know we assume טמא. tamei. And again we
asked beforehand, what’s the difference between flesh and garment, and we said
there are cases where it matters. על בשרה, al besarah, מאי לאו
mai lav כי האי גוונא, ki hai gavna, don’t we mean these
cases that even though it’s like weird the configuration we’re going to
be stricter because it’s on her body itself? If it was on
her clothes we would be lenient with this configuration, but on her
body we’re going to be more strict and assume it’s from her.
So that’s a pretty reasonable position. גמרא Gemara says: לא, lo, no,
דילמא דהוי כרצועה, dilma dehvei kiretsuah, maybe that case where we’re being
strict is when it’s literally, it’s like a, it’s like a straight
line down, you know, on her body lengthwise, and then we’ll be
strict, but in these weird configurations, not. But of course if it
was a straight line down you’d be strict also on the clothes.
Not clear what it means we’re being more strict by the בשר,
basar, so anyway. But anyway the גמרא Gemara makes a reasonable argument
that because it’s directly on her body we’d be more strict, it
does not come out with a clear, clear conclusion of how we
deal with these cases.
Does רצועה retsuah mean a whip?
A yeah, a,
I'm not a whip, I mean a רצועה retsuah just means like
a, like a strap, yeah something like that, yeah like
a, like a straight line.
Yeah, I mean, no, these are describing shapes, I don’t think they’re
describing the causes. All these things are the description of the
shape. ההיא איתתא, Hahi iteta, now we get to a case, אשתכח
לה דמא במשיכתא, ishtakach lah dama bemeshichta, a woman found blood on
her loom, okay, there was a drop of blood on some of
the threads on the loom. אתאי לקמיה דרבי ינאי, Atai lekamei deRabbi
Yannai, she came to Rabbi Yannai. אמר לה, amar lah, he said
to her: תיזיל ותיתי, teizil veteiti, walk back and forth the way
you’re walking, let’s see if you, in your natural walking, you step
over the loom area. And if you do, then we can assume
it came from you, but if your normal way of your moving
around this room you’ll never step over the loom area, then it
must have come from elsewhere. So the גמרא Gemara says: והתניא vehatanya
אין שונין בטהרות, ein shonin betaharot, don’t we say that we don’t
sort of do a redo by טהרות, taharot, meaning we have a
doubt where something came from, we don’t say that the guy or
the gal, like, do what you were doing before and we’ll make
our determination based on what it looks like now. Who knows, maybe
the way you’re doing it now is not the way you did
it before, so we normally say you don’t try again. So the
גמרא Gemara says: כי אמרנו אין שונין לקולא, ki amrinu ein shonin
lekula, we don’t do that if we’re trying to be lenient, we
say do it again, oh we see that you don’t walk over,
then we can be lenient. We don’t say this to be lenient,
אבל לחומרא שונין, aval lechumra shonin, we can say that to be
strict. So here, basically, if it was סתם stam on the loom
we would assume it's not from her, so he’s saying but walk
again, that’s in order to say, but then I see that you
do walk over it, then I’ll be strict. So we might want
to sort of check again and say let me see how you
were acting, as a, if, if we have a doubt and we
want to be strict, but we won’t use that again if we’re
inclined to be strict and use the redo as a basis for
being lenient. Okay, so anyway, but that is yet another question about
how we try to determine where it came from. I will say
interestingly, as we're coming to an end of a מסכת Masechet whatever,
that the גמרא Gemara says משכיתא דשלום, Mashkita d'Shalom, but if you
look at רש״י Rashi like pretty much straight across, רש״י Rashi says
עם המסכת דשמשון מתרגמינן עם משכיתא. im hamasechet d'Shimshon m'targemnan im mashkita.
So משכיתא Mashkita means a loom because the word in שמשון Shimshon
in שופטים Shoftim that refers to the loom that is a מסכת.
Masechet. And so מסכת Masechet is actually interesting, it's a name of
a tractate. So a loom is the thing that you actually make
the cloth on, or is the loom the thing you're spinning the
thread?
I think the loom is the thing you're making the cloth on,
right? Anyway,
it is an interesting association with text, textile, this and in a
couple of languages the whole theme of weaving and cloth and text
and books. You can sort of do a little research of your
own, but I thought I'd point that out. Okay, moving on. היתה
פושטתה, Haista pushtata, if she took off her garment and used it
as a blanket, it doesn't matter where it's on the garment, you
say it could have come from her because the blanket moves around.
תני, Tani, we taught in a ברייתא, Brayta, אמר רבי אלעזר ברבי
יוסי, Amar Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Yossi, דבר זה הוריתי בעיר רומי לאיסור,
Davar zeh horeiti b'ir Romi l'issur, I ruled this way in Rome.
So today, had a lot to do with Rome, right?
Yeah. I ruled this way in Rome that the case where a
woman was using it as a blanket and it was on a
like the top of the garment and I still said it's a
problem. וכשבאתי אצל חכמים שבדרום, Uch'shebati etzel chachamim shebadarom, when I came
to the rabbis in the north, interesting where's the north, the north
of Italy? Anyway,
שבדרום, shebadarom, the north of Israel, I guess. But interesting, שבדרום. shebadarom.
Anyway, I came to the rabbis in the south, אמרו לי יפה
הורית. amru li yafeh horeita. They said you ruled correctly.
תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. ארוכה שלבשה חלוקה של קצרה, Arucha shelavsha chaluka
shel ktzara, if a tall woman is wearing the garment of a
short one. If you're wearing the garment of a short one, then
the below the belt area might be up above your waist area.
Okay, or קצרה שלבשה חלוקה של ארוכה. ktzara shelavsha chaluka shel arucha.
A short woman is wearing the garment of a tall woman. So
in her case, her below the belt might be
above below the waist, might be above the waist on the garment
itself, right? Because you got the idea.
אם מגיע כנגד בית התורפה של ארוכה שתיהן טמאות. Im magiya keneged
beit haturpa shel arucha shteihem tmeiot. If there's a stain on the
that opposite the waist area of the tall woman, then they're both
טמאות. tmeiot. Because obviously if it's the waist on the tall area,
if it's on the garment a short woman is wearing, if it's
below the waist of the tall, then it's certainly lower the body.
And for the tall woman herself, if it's below the waist of
the garment she's wearing, then it's below her waist, so it's a
problem. אם לאו, Im lav, if it's not below the waist, if
it's above the waist area of the tall woman, ארוכה טהורה, arucha
tehora, the tall woman is טהורה. tehora. If the garment she's wearing
it's above the waist, so fine, she's טהורה. tehora. וקצרה טמאה, uktzara
tmeia, the short woman is טמאה, tmeia, because even though it's above
the waist on the garment, it might still be below her waist,
right? The garment she's wearing is too big, is too long for
her, so it might be below the mid-area of the garment but
still below her waist.
Okay, תניא אידך, tanya idach, we taught in another ברייתא. brayta. בדקה
חלוקה והשאילתה לחברתה, Badka chaluka v'hishpiltah l'chavertah, she checked her garment, said
it was stain-free, and then lent it to her friend. And then
the friend finds a stain on it. היא טהורה וחברתה תולה בה.
Hi tehora v'chavertah tola bah. She is טהורה tehora and her
friend can say oh yeah, I assume the stain came from you
because you lent me the garment. So according to the simple read
of this ברייתא, brayta, they're both טהורות. tehorot. There's a stain on
it, each one assumes the stain came from the other person. I
checked, I know there was no stain, you borrowed it, and then
you're saying that I'm you're gonna assume there was a stain, fine,
so we're both טהורות. tehorot. The גמרא Gemara does not like that.
אמר רב ששת, Amar Rav Sheshet, ולעניין דינא תנן. ul'inyan dina tnan.
This is only when it comes to דיני ממונות, dinei mamonot, meaning
if you give me back my garment and I say what's this
stain and you said oh that stain, that was there when you
lent it to me, I assumed, and I want you to pay
for the dry cleaning bills, then you can say I refuse to
pay for the dry cleaning bill, I'm claiming that the stain was
there when you lent it to me. Okay, so that's when we
say that the second one can blame it on the first. If
there's no evidence, then I can't prove that, you know, it's like
when you rent a car, they make you go around and check
off where there's a little nick, right? So if there's no evidence,
I can't make her pay for the dry cleaning bill. אבל לעניין
טומאה, Aval l'inyan tumah, when it comes to
טומאה, tumah, היא טהורה וחברתה טמאה. hi tehora v'chavertah tmeia. So the
owner of the dress is טהורה tehora and the other one is
טמאה tmeia because I checked it, I say that it was that
way, and you don't
know definitely otherwise, you have to go by my say-so. So I'm
okay and we'll assume you are the source of the stain and
you are טמאה, tmeia, the second one. So now the גמרא Gemara
says מאי שנא מהא דתניא, mai shna m'ha d'tanya, how is it
different from that which we taught in the
ברייתא: brayta: שתי נשים שנתעסקו בציפור אחד ואין בו אלא כסלע דם,
shtei nashim shenitasu b'tzipor echad v'ein bo ela k'sela dam, two women
were both dealing with one chicken or whatever it was and the
whole amount of blood in the entire chicken was the size of
a סלע, sela, a certain coin. I don't know if it's a
chicken, whatever it was, a tiny little bird. ונמצא כסלע על זו
וכסלע על זו, V'nimtza k'sela al zo v'k'sela al zo, and now
they both leave and both of their garments have a stain the
size of this סלע. sela. Now it couldn't have both come from
the same chicken. So what do you do?
שתיהן טמאות. shteihem tmeiot. They're both טמאות. tmeiot. Each one can't say
oh my stain was from the chicken, because then what about the
other person's stain? So since neither one has the right to know
that theirs is
okay.
So why is that different? There you're going to say they're both
טמא, tameh, here you're only going to say the second one. So
the difference actually is quite obvious, תוספות Tosafot doesn't even understand a
question. שאני התם דאיכא סלע יתירה, shani hatam d'ika sela yesira, no,
there, there's an extra size of an extra stain that can't be
attributed elsewhere, one person, and nobody has a right to say that
theirs is the okay one. Here the woman is able to say,
"I checked, I know for certain that it was not my stain."
So when she says that, the other woman is stuck with it.
But in this case, since no one can assert definitely that theirs
is the okay one, then they both are stuck with it.
תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, לבשה שלוש חלוקות הבדוקים לה, lavsha shalosh chalukos
habdukin lah, she wore three layers of garments and she checked all
of them.
So, אם יכולה לתלות תולה ואפילו בתחתון, im yechola litlos tola va'afilu
betachton, if she has a stain that she can say came from
elsewhere, then, then she, like she walked into a butcher area, then
even if it's on the inner garment she can say that's where
it's from. ואם אינה יכולה לתלות, ve'im eina yechola litlos, and if
she has no, nothing to make it sort of blame it on,
she's not walking in a butcher area, אינה תולה ואפילו בעליון, eina
tola va'afilu be'elyon, even the outer one, right? So this is
basically, if she has something to base it on you're good even
on an inner garment, if you don't have something to base it
on then even the outer garment you're no good.
אינה תולה ואפילו בעליון, eina tola va'afilu be'elyon, כיצד, keitzad, how is
this true? עברה בשוק של טבחים, avra beshuk shel tabachim, if she
goes through a butcher
area, תולה ואפילו בתחתון, tola va'afilu betachton, she could assume even a
stain on the inner garment came from there. לא עברה בשוק של
טבחים, lo avra beshuk shel tabachim, if she didn't, אפילו בעליון אינה
תולה, afilu be'elyon eina tola, even the outer garment she cannot make
it depend. Now of course the question to be asking here is,
like the גמרא Gemara before by the סלע, sela, let's say it's
on the, only on the inner garment and not on the outer
ones and she walked through the marketplace, maybe she can't be תולה.
tola. Let's say it's only on the outer and not on the
inner, then even if she didn't walk through the marketplace, how'd it
get on the outer without being on the inner if it came
from her? So there are all these factors which the גמרא Gemara
never completely systematizes about trying to figure out where it came from,
but clearly this is the principle of being תולה. tola. I want
to at least read the next משנה mishna because this is very
important, both in terms of women bringing their cases and both in
terms of another dividing line between פשט peshat and הלכה. halacha. So
let's take a look. תולה, tola, so first the משנה mishna begins
here with principles we've seen, תולה בכל דבר שיכולה לתלות, tola bechol
davar sheyechola litlos, if she can blame it on something else, she
makes it dependent on those. שחטה בהמה חיה ועוף, shachta behema chaya
ve'of, if she was שוחט shocheit animals, she was שוחט shocheit by
the
way,
notice, בהמה, behema, yeah, first תוספות Tosafot in חולין Chullin says that
a woman could be a שוחט, shocheit, it's clear. נתעסקה בכתמים, nisaska
bechtamim, if she was, you don't need תוספות, Tosafot, right. If she
was dealing with stains, why? I don't know, checking other women's stains,
other purposes, או שישבה בצד העוסקים בהם, o sheyashva betzad ha'oskim bahem,
or she was sitting by people that were dealing with blood, הרגה
מאכולת, harga macholes, if she squashed a louse, הרי זה תולה בה,
harei ze tola ba, she can blame it on any of those
things.
It's usually a bloodstain, it'd be dry wouldn't it?
Or if in a case where it could have spread. עד כמה
תולה, ad kama tola, so how, how big of a stain, meaning
particularly with the louse, because a louse is pretty small, עד כמה
תולה,
ad kama tola, I'm not
sure, maybe she's checking other women's stains, it's not clear what נתעסקה
nisaska is. It could be her own. Yeah, could be. It's not
clear. So anyway, עד כמה תולה, ad kama tola, how big of
a stain can you say is a louse? רבי חנינא בן אנטיגנוס
אומר עד כגריס של פול, Rebbi Chanina ben Antignos omer ad kegris
shel pol, until a, basically a half size of a bean, which
is basically the גריס, gris, which we say nowadays is a, like
a penny or a nickel. For just the louse? Just for the
louse. But then he goes further to say ואף על פי שלא
הרגה, ve'af al pi shelo harga, even if she didn't kill a
louse, lice are so prevalent that any stain smaller than the size
of a גריס gris I will assume is a louse. And this
becomes a critical הלכה halacha in הלכות כתמים, hilchos ketamim, that we
say that a stain smaller than the size of a penny or
nickel, of a גריס, gris, is not a problem. Why? Based on
the principle that it might be a louse, even though nowadays we
don't have lice all over the place, basically the אחרונים Acharonim pretty
much universally say, this is a formal rabbinic category of stains, they
decided that the size was a גריס gris and that remains the
שיעור shiur even when there's nothing to base it on. It is
all thanks to רבי חנינא בן אנטיגנוס Rebbi Chanina ben Antignos who
says she doesn't have to have killed the louse. All thanks to
the lice. Okay. What do you say?
It says here but she was נתעסקה, nisaska,
אף על פי שלא הרגה, af al pi shelo harga, no, no,
no, it's going on the last case, the last case is הרגה
מאכולת harga macholes and he says לא הרגה. lo harga. You can
always blame it on a louse if it's smaller than the size
of a
גריס. gris. ותולה בבנה ובבעלה, vetola bivna uv'ba'ala, she can also even
if it's maybe her husband or her son has a nosebleed or
has some type of a wound that was the source of it,
and if that's a reasonable thing to say that it came from
them, you can say it came from them. אם יש בה מכה,
im yesh ba maka, if he has a wound, והיא יכולה להתגלע
ולהוציא דם, vehi yechola lehisgaleya ulehotzi dam, even if it's sort of
has a crust, not crusted over,
anyway, scabbed over, whatever, if it could expose, be exposed and still
bleed, הרי זה תולה, harei ze tola, then she can say it's
based on that even though it's not currently bleeding, because maybe it
opened up and it bled. And then where it was... Right, depending
where it is. מעשה באשה אחת, ma'aseh b'isha achas, there's a story,
שבאה לפני רבי עקיבא, sheba'a lifnei Rabbi Akiva, she came in front
of Rabbi Akiva. אמרה לו, amrah lo, she said to him, ראיתי
כתם, ra'isi kesem, I had a stain. אמר לה, amar lah, he
said to her, שמא מכה הייתה בך, shema makah hayisa bach, maybe
you've had a wound somewhere in your body? אמרה לו הן, amrah
lo hen, yes, וחייתה, v'chayasa, but it healed. אמר לה, amar lah,
שמא יכולה להיגלות ולהוציא דם, shema yechola lehigalot ul'hotzi dam, maybe it's
possible that the wound could open up still and blood could still
come from it? אמרה לו הן, amrah lo hen, you know what,
that's possible. ותטהרה רבי עקיבא, v'sit'harah Rabbi Akiva, says fine, you're טהור,
tahor, don't worry about it. And here you have like this whole
פנקס pinkas worth of being leniencies around particularly issues around stains, כתם
kesem as opposed to ראייה, re'iyah, which is why שמואל's Shmuel הלכה
halacha is so critical. So, ראה תלמידיו מסתכלין זה בזה, ra'ah talmidav
mistaklin zeh bazeh, he saw students like looking at one another, what
was this crazy פסק? psak? Maybe it could have opened up and
maybe it could have bled, I mean right now it's healed. So,
אמר להם, amar lahem, he said to them, מה דבר קשה בעיניכם,
mah davar kashah b'eineichem, why is this so problematic in your eyes?
שלא אמרו חכמים הדבר להחמיר אלא להקל, shelo amru chachamim hadavar l'hachmir
ela l'hakel, when it comes to stains we are not trying to
be, I mean the
whole category of stains is strict, obviously, but once we have said
stains, we don't look to be strict, we look to be lenient.
שנאמר, shen'emar, the פסוק pasuk says, ואשה כי תהיה זבה, v'ishah ki
sihiyeh zava, if a woman flows, דם יהיה זובה בבשרה, dam yihyeh
zuvah bivsarah, blood flowing in her flesh, דם ולא כתם, dam v'lo
kesem, blood and not a stain. And what does that mean? So
until now I've been telling you there are two ways of understanding
the difference between ראייה re'iyah and כתם. kesem. One is if there's
an element of doubt it's a stain, if there's not it's a
ראייה re'iyah and it's, you know, biblical. The other is שמואל's Shmuel
lack of הרגשה. hargashah. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva presents a third possibility,
and רש''י Rashi in other גמרות, Gemaras, when he discusses the difference
what makes something a כתם, kesem, quotes רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. Says
דם ולא כתם, dam v'lo kesem, which basically seems to be that
if you see it coming from your body, then it's what the
Torah is describing. If you find it after the fact on your
skin, on your clothes or whatever, that's not the case of the
Torah, that's only Rabbinic. So that it could be that like שמואל,
Shmuel, even if it's definitely, even if it's definitely from you, if
you find it as a stain and don't see it coming from
your body, then it's only Rabbinic. That's if you take רבי עקיבא's
Rabbi Akiva דרשה drasha to its logical conclusion and it's important to
note that although the גמרא Gemara doesn't play with this דרשה drasha
too much, רש''י Rashi throughout ש''ס Shas quotes רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
in explaining what makes something a כתם kesem and only Rabbinic. Let's
just end the משנה. Mishnah.
How far back are you concerned
when it's Rabbinic?
When you mean how far back? You see a כתם, kesem, you
have to wonder where it came from unless you can make it
dependent on something else.
Since the last time you checked there?
Yeah, yeah, yeah, we discussed that before, it has to be,
yeah. So, עד שהוא נתון תחת הכר ונמצא עליו דם עגול טהור,
ed shehu nasun tachas hakar v'nimtza alav dam agol tahor, last case,
if you had a checking cloth under the pillow so it was
under the pillow all night, maybe some little louse or something got
squashed on it. So if it is a circular stain then it's
טהור tahor because that would come from a louse or something of
the similar. משוך, mashuch, if it's elongated, טמא, tamei, because then it
obviously came through the act of using it to check. You would
not have that if it was just a squashed insect. דברי רבי
אלעזר בר צדוק. divrei Rabbi Elazar bar Tzadok. We've quoted that before.
It's going back about making things dependent on other things, linking them
up. All right.